<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Marty Romero</title>
 <link href="http://martyromero.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://martyromero.me/"/>
 <updated>2016-05-31T01:04:18-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://martyromero.me</id>
 <author>
   <name>Marty Romero</name>
   <email>martyromero@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>From Faith to Crisis in Three Acts (Act 1)</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/faith-to-crisis-in-three-acts-act-1-a-closet-holly-roller"/>
   <updated>2016-05-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/faith-to-crisis-in-three-acts-act-1-a-closet-holly-roller</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/posts/elder-romero-tmm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elder Romero - Texas McAllen Mission 1997.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em class=&quot;image-caption clearfix&quot;&gt;Elder Romero - Texas McAllen Mission 1997.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-closet-holly-roller&quot;&gt;A closet “Holly Roller”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before spending two years a missionary for the Mormon church, I was timid about having religious conversations with anyone. This was particularly pronounced during my junior high school years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mormon church use to have a program where boys ages twelve through eighteen were paired up with their fathers once a month—typically on the first Saturday of the month—to collect donations from members of the local congregation. Kids whose dad was absent in the home—like me—were paired up with male adult members who didn’t have boys of their own or whose boys were too young. I didn’t mind doing it, but I was terrified that I would be spotted by my school friends in a white shirt and tie performing church duty. The Mormon church that I attended was in the same neighborhood where I attended school, so some Saturdays I faked being sick to not go. To this day I don’t know why or where I picked up the idea that church-going people were weak and ridiculous, and being found out by my friends that I was one of them (church-going) would have been terribly embarrassing to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned to compartmentalize life and to not allow any overlap between my different roles early on. I couldn’t bare the thought of being discovered by my friends as a “Holly Roller.” At school I was a popular graffiti tagger, but on weekends I had a secret identity. I was a “Holly Roller.” On weekdays I was “cool”, I tagged public buses, I was funny, I didn’t put up with crap from anyone. But on Sundays I was “pure.” I prayed, I fasted, I read scriptures, I said things like “I know this church is true.” I was  quiet and timid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I graduated from high school in 1992 and four years later I decided to fulfill my expected two-year duty to the Mormon church by serving a full-time mission. Missionary service marked the first of two changes in my religious point of view. As a Missionary I found that most people were not only willing to, but excited to share the most intimate details about their religious experience with me. For the majority it was comforting to speak about their  belief in God, their feelings about church, morality, purity and salvation. When they spoke, they didn’t sound ridiculous and they didn’t appear weak. I was wrong to have thought so. I decided that I had compartmentalized my life the wrong way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-room-in-my-house&quot;&gt;A Room in My House&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never felt the same urgency or excitement about serving a full-time mission as my friends did. Boys were expected to begin their Missionary service at nineteen, but at that age I found it hard to speak about religion with anyone still. So, I was twenty-two when I entered the Missionary Training Center in Provo Utah. If I could describe my religious point of view at this stage in life, I would describe it in terms of a house. My life was divided into different “rooms.” Church, spirituality and religiosity happened on Sundays in a specific room. There were other rooms in my life. There was a room where work life took place, another for school life, and yet another for my social life . There was a room for every different aspect of my life with no overlap between them. It made it easy for me to move from one area of responsibility to the next without needing to reconcile any discrepancies or resolve conflicts between them. I could record and be paid for unworked hours by my employer Monday through Friday and learn about honesty and integrity at church on Sunday without feeling guilt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned home from serving the Mormon church in 1999. I was back in familiar places amongst friends and family, but I was wasn’t the same. I had been changed by my missionary experience. I returned home with a deep desire to wear out my life serving God—which to me was synonymous with serving the LDS church. Everything I did became an appendage to my religion. My academic success or failure, my social life, my professional work, my relationships etc., it  was all a shaped by my faith (or lack thereof). In the mission field, I took the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ldsmissionarymoms.com/notablequotes/MMCsign.shtml&quot; title=&quot;LDS Missionary Commision&quot;&gt;LDS Missionary Commission&lt;/a&gt; to heart and strived to live by its principles when I got home—particularly these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…He (Christ) has chosen me to represent Him—to stand in His place, to say and do what He Himself would say and do… My voice is His voice, and my acts are His acts; my doctrine is His doctrine. My Commission is to do what He wants done; to say what He wants said; to be a living modern witness in word and in deed of the divinity of his great and marvelous Latter-day work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My life was a house made up of various rooms each with a specific purpose. Serving as a missionary didn’t stop me from compartmentalizing the same way, but it did changed the space in my life where religion happened. Religion use have a room of its own. Now religion happened in a common area—the kitchen. More specifically religion became the stew on the stove. It became the aroma and that aroma permitted every other room in the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;god-salvation-and-morality&quot;&gt;God, Salvation and Morality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of returned missionaries, I was “faithful” to the Mormon religious traditions I believed that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Mormon church was the only &lt;em&gt;true and living church&lt;/em&gt; on the face of the earth, restored through the hands of Joseph Smith.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Book of Mormon was a historical, ancient book written in a modified version of Hebrew and Egyptian by ancient holy men living in the American continent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Book of Mormon had been translated by Joseph Smith through the power of God.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only within the Mormon church, the legitimate authority to pronounce blessings, interpret scripture, and issue  proclamations in God’s name—the Priesthood—could be found.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About God, I believed that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;God had a physical body of flesh and bone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;God was all-knowing, all-powerful and all-good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;God dwelt in heaven.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;God’s love for me was such that He allowed Jesus to be put to death and that through His sacrifice I could repent of my sins and return to live with Him in heaven.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;God was involved in the most minute of my life’s details. From the most insignificant to the most important issues, God was literally experiencing life with me. I was never alone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Through prayer I could have a conversation with God. If I were attentive and keenly tuned, through prayer I could experience communion with God.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salvation in the Mormon church is shrouded in controversy because some of the doctrines that make up salvation in the LDS church are quite peculiar and unique. I never objected to any of them, but I didn’t feel a strong conviction that they were all true. What I did believed about salvation was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was a plan laid out from before the world was created, and became operational at Gethsemane and Golgotha.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was required to accept the sacrifice of Jesus on my behalf.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was required to be baptized by water (fully submerged by a male member of the Mormon church possessing authentic authority to do so), and by the Holy Ghost.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salvation entailed an eternity of indescribable joy for me and my family in the presence of God.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salvation was a lifelong process that had happened (see 1), was happening, and would ultimately happen at some point in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To borrow a metaphor from C.S. Lewis, the mechanics of salvation—faith and works—operated in a fashion similar to a pair of scissors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Christians have often disputed as to whether what leads the Christian home is good actions, or faith in Christ … it does seem to me like asking which blade in a pair of scissors is most necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;C. S. Lewis, Mere Christianity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to morality, I  only ever had one belief. It was this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Morality is represented by a life that exhibits behavior in harmony with an individual’s religious convictions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;as-the-dew-in-the-morning&quot;&gt;As the Dew in the Morning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next eighteen to twenty years that followed I changed. The change was slow. It happened as the dew that forms on grass in the mornings. It was gradual and with such stealth that it was just short of invisible, but I changed almost everything that I believed about these three things; God, Salvation and Morality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em class=&quot;image-caption clearfix&quot;&gt;This is part 1 of a 3 part blog series entitled Faith to Crisis in Three Acts &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Debate Over Graffiti as Crime or Art is Pointless (part 2 of 2)</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/the-debate-over-graffiti-as-crime-or-art-is-pointless-2-of-2"/>
   <updated>2016-04-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/the-debate-over-graffiti-as-crime-or-art-is-pointless-2-of-2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;style&gt;.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed//9vjgwWvnfhU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em class=&quot;image-caption clearfix&quot;&gt;Hex TGO and Slick battle at the levits yard 1989. Los Angeles.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-two&quot;&gt;Part two&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part two of my argument for graffiti. My argument is not so much for graffiti to be made legal—though it might seem so. Instead, what I try to make a case for is that graffiti&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; serves a positive function in any community when we consider how we use and experience our public spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand my position, we first have to get on the same page about what I mean when I use the word “graffiti.” Most arguments for or against graffiti fail to do this, and by not defining the term, it is assumed that all graffiti is equal. Though I will admit, that to the average person graffiti is graffiti no matter who wrote it or why. But that isn’t the case. For example, gang graffiti is not the same as graffiti by a “tagger.” Gang graffiti is typically used to mark the gang’s territory, declare a death sentence on a rival gang member by crossing out his name, or as a roll call of the gang’s members themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graffiti by taggers does not make the claim to territory the way gang graffiti does. Also unlike gang graffiti, crossing out the name of another tagger is not seen as a death sentence, but a challenge to the other tagger to see who can paint/tag better and more. Painting over the work of one tagger by another without retaliation is common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;definitions&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of graffiti by &lt;em&gt;The American Heritage Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Drawings or inscriptions made on a wall or other surface, usually so as to be seen by the public. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the official definition of graffiti makes no mention of its legality. Of course, I am not implying that we base our laws on a dictionary’s explanation of a particular term. But I do advocate that we consider graffiti from a broader perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the State’s definition of graffiti:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“As used in this section, the term ‘graffiti or other inscribed material’ includes any unauthorized inscription, word, figure, mark, or design, that is written, marked, etched, scratched, drawn, or painted on real or personal property.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keyword in the State’s definition of graffiti does not focus on the act of, but the “unauthorized” act of graffiti which is illegal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-issue-with-graffiti&quot;&gt;The real issue with graffiti&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this regards, the focus should not be on graffiti itself, but the means by which we attain authorization. By both definitions—the classic and the more sectarian definition in California’s penal code—anything that is public is potentially graffiti. For example; Nextel billboards, Nike ads on bus shelters or a movie bill on the side of a construction site. The reason why these corporations are authorized to install their ads on public space is the amount of money they are willing and able to spend. Graffiti, on the other hand, is labeled a crime because no one corporation is making money from it&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to believe that “money isn’t everything.” But the truth is that when we accept as normal the fact that only those with money have a voice, then we are saying that money indeed &lt;em&gt;is everything&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before graffiti is labeled illegal, we need to examine the merit of the laws that makes it so. Not long ago, laws forced black folks to sit in the back of the bus, Mexicans to visit public swimming pools only on cleaning days. Thankfully, those laws have changed. The point that I am trying to make is that the merits of the law do not always reflect what is right and what is wrong, nor what does or does not contribute positively to any one community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current laws prohibit the right to public space—unless we can dish out a hefty dime for it. Graffiti challenges that. So do I!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I am using a specific definition of graffiti. Vic does an excellent job of explaining here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/1T3QoiF&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://bit.ly/1T3QoiF&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/1V1kZ3P&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The American Heritage Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/1V1lCKM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;California Penal Code Section 594-625c&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is changing. As companies are finding that they can use graffiti to target younger consumers, they have commissioning graffiti artists to paint “mini-murals” throughout inner cities advertising their products. &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/1V1pfQU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Here is an interesting article of one corporation’s efforts to “fit in”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dear Cheating Spouse...</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/dear-cheating-spouse"/>
   <updated>2016-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/dear-cheating-spouse</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your first marriage is over. Would you like to create a second one together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You will be rebuilding a new life after an affair; the question becomes, will you be doing it together as a couple, or on your own?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/P2AUat93a8Q&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;- Esther Perel - &lt;em&gt;Why Happy Couples Cheat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Debate Over Graffiti as Crime or Art is Pointless (part 1 of 2)</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/the-debate-over-graffiti-as-crime-or-art-is-pointless"/>
   <updated>2016-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/the-debate-over-graffiti-as-crime-or-art-is-pointless</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/posts/graffiti-good.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;KaterOne, Visions Crew 2005, East Los Angeles.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;KaterOne, Visions Crew 2005, East Los Angeles.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-debate&quot;&gt;The debate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, I wrote graffiti for the thrill, anonymity, and recognition from other graffiti writers. As a graffiti writer, I didn’t realize the passionate debate over graffiti as art or crime like I do now—a discussion that is pointless in my opinion. A more productive question to answer by those on either side of the fence is, what is the role of graffiti in our public space? The obvious answer—some would argue—is that graffiti should NOT play a role and that it ought to be eradicated. Well, I’d like to challenge that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My school newspaper recently wrote an article about how much it was going to cost to remove graffiti from the L.A. river walls. The writer wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…there are no positive effects of graffiti to any community, and those caught doing it should be locked away and the key thrown away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argued that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…because graffiti by definition is a crime, it cannot be approached as anything else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writer did note that commissioned works—even those painted by graffiti artist and clearly graffiti—were NOT “really” graffiti, because they had authorization. The problem with arguments about the legality of graffiti or those that defend it as art is that they ignore aspects of graffiti that relate to how we use our public spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-the-debate-is-pointless&quot;&gt;Why is the debate is pointless&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say that there are no positive contributions by graffiti implies a set of criteria by which we determine what provides and what does not provide value. What is that criterion? Who defines it? Is the criterion accurate? Most people would say that the law sets the criteria, but it would only take a basic history lesson to point out that some laws can be unjust. When we submit law a the ultimate criteria for what is and what is not legal or of value, then we must submit the amount of corporate control, immigration, civil rights, etc. through that criterion—which we don’t. If we solely rely on the denotation of graffiti to ascribe its value, we are forced to accept that what is natural is often socially constructed to the interest of some more than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-graffitis-contribution&quot;&gt;What is graffiti’s contribution?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I propose that graffiti and graffiti writers’ contributions are valuable, particularly when we speak of public space. The value is in recognizing the socially constructed truths and political agendas that influence our culture, society and communities in ways that we may not want. Graffiti keeps these truths and agendas on check by constantly challenging them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, people might argue that advertising or popular culture does not influence them, but what they mean is that the apparent messages of these cultural productions do not influence them. Adds that try to sell Wendy’s instead of McDonalds, or Pepsi instead of Coke may not have a real impact on individuals. But the underlying myth of consumerism that these ads present when added up to all of the thousands of unrecognized retellings of the consumer myth do influence the nation into believing that the myth of consumerism is not a myth, but is the natural state of human affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today, communities produce almost nothing. As an employee or a student, we are required to produce some things: reports, call logs, sales, etc. But outside of our role as employees, or students, what do we produce? Most of us do not grow or raise our food, we don’t make our clothes, and only a few in the community make their own music or entertainment. Some participate in athletics once in a while, but other than sports and dancing there is little left in society for humans to produce. Instead, we have become consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each time that graffiti is produced, it speaks against the consumerism myth such that it becomes an identity marker of a community.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Discovering My Masturbation Myths</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/discovering-my-masturbation-myths"/>
   <updated>2016-04-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/discovering-my-masturbation-myths</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;style&gt;.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed//zRkPU1fKchI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;something-to-hide&quot;&gt;Something to Hide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the summer when I discovered masturbation. It was an incredible three months that came to an end in September at the start of a new school year. I recall the anxiety vividly that I felt over not being able to enjoy quiet mornings romancing myself while mom and my sister were at work. I must have been eleven or twelve that summer. At that age, I hadn’t heard the term “masturbation”, and if I had, I wouldn’t have been able to associate it with the beautifully raw gesture that left me numb with joy when I was finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in a household that was NOT sex-friendly. By that, I mean that sex was a topic not to be spoken of openly. We ignored the “sexy” scenes in R rated movies and pretended that we didn’t understand the innuendos of TV commercials. No one ever told me that sex or masturbation was wrong, but it’s a lesson that I learned regardless. I learned—like we all do—to NOT talk about sex and to hide my natural curiosity about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-story&quot;&gt;My Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t help that I was raised up in the Mormon Church. My mother is a beautiful traditional Mexican mom. Single that she was, she raised my sister and I as best she knew how. What that meant in practical terms is that others imparted a lot of our ethical, moral, and just general-life lessons. Many of those lessons came from the Mormon Church.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mormonthink.com/QUOTES/masturbation.htm&quot; title=&quot;LDS Quotes on the Topic of Masturbation&quot;&gt;Mormonism teaches implicitly and explicitly that masturbation is not only wrong but sinful&lt;/a&gt;. I grew up listening to leaders of the Mormon Church say things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…If you are tempted to masturbate, think of having to bathe in a tub of worms, and eat several of them as you do the act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a year after I discovered that I could… well, you know. The bishop of my local Mormon Church congregation took it upon himself to gather all the young men twelve to fifteen years old, and graphically describe what masturbation was and how it made young boys “evil.” He described something very different from my experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “man of God” was telling me that what I was doing was a “sexual sin” and that “sexual sins” ranked right next to murder in the eyes of God. To me, the pleasure that I derived during my quiet mornings at home were special. The sad thing about this experience is that it encapsulated the attitude towards sex and masturbation by everyone who was raising me, and it changed me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had learned that my bishop was Jesus Christs’ mouthpiece. And he was telling me that I was “evil.” So, some of my very first lies &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; have been to myself. I don’t remember convincing myself that I was &lt;em&gt;NOT&lt;/em&gt;, but I must have!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I wish someone would have assured me that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The LDS Church leaders were wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That like anything, masturbation could become an unhealthy behavior, but that it is neither evil nor sinful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That being highly sexual and sensitive was not something that I needed to hide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am forty-two years old now, and I am married to a beautiful woman. We don’t have a perfect marriage—much of what is wrong with our companionship has been my own doing. It seems clear in retrospect that a lot of the challenges today go back to those early lessons. I am just now beginning to understand how damaging it was for me not to have a space where I could be open about sex. And by that, I don’t mean that I wish I could have been more promiscuous or sexual, just more open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I wish, is that my mother and my Church leaders could have been made to sit through this beautiful and raw TED talk. Thank you &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.teeshamorgan.com/&quot; title=&quot;Dr. Teesha Morgan&quot;&gt;Dr. Teesha Morgan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Last Night I Saw My Dad</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/the-last-night-i-saw-my-dad"/>
   <updated>2016-03-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/the-last-night-i-saw-my-dad</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/posts/dad-last-night.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My dad standing in front of a palm tree.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em class=&quot;image-caption clearfix&quot;&gt;In his 30s, dad while serving time at Islas Marias Federal Prison in Mexico.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mom&quot;&gt;Mom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mom left dad when I was five years old. During the weeks leading up to her decision, she thought of every possible excuse to stay, but there was a way out of every single one. Now and then mom opens up about the things that she considered. She feared not being able to raise two kids on her own. My sister was born without her left leg and caring for her would be difficult. She also thought about how much my sister and I would miss dad, me in particular—I was his favorite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once decided, mom had to figure out a way to leave without raising the suspicion that we would not be coming back. She packed all of our clothes in boxes and had them shipped to my aunt in &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/THHOTWBs8ZQ&quot; title=&quot;The colonia where I grew up&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ensenada&lt;/a&gt; a few days before we left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step in her plan was to pack wood and a few rocks in empty boxes and stack them neatly inside the closet. The purpose was to give my dad the impression that we were coming back and that she was merely making sure our “clothes” would be neatly waiting for us upon our return. Mom had had enough. Dad cheated on her, abused her (verbally, physically, and sexually). Mom was ready to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dad&quot;&gt;Dad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad drove us to the bus station. While we waited to board the bus, dad kept me close to him. I remember holding his hand and feeling that he didn’t want to let go of me. I thought he had figured it out! That somehow he knew we weren’t coming back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we boarded the bus, he knelt beside me and kissed me on my cheek. I remember the prickly feeling of his mustache against my face and the strong smell of cigar. He tightened his grip on my hand and whispered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am going to follow the bus for as long as I can, so be on the look out for me ok?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;me&quot;&gt;Me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those were the last words he said to me. That was his way of saying good-bye. On the bus, mom didn’t say much, but she held my hand the entire trip. As the bus got on the road, I kept looking out the window for dad’s blue El Camino with the dirty white camper. A minute later, I saw his car cut in front of us. That gesture was as if he were talking to me and I burned it into memory. I stared at his car through the window, afraid to look away for fear that I might lose him. Some short distance later, I saw dad’s car make a right turn, but the bus that we were on kept on going straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the years went by and I got older, I always yearned to tell him that I had seen his car that night many years ago. And that I loved him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dad passed away ten years ago today. Sometimes I still miss him.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Things I believe (and two that I don&#39;t)</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/things-i-believe"/>
   <updated>2015-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/things-i-believe</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have spent a lot of my time trying to describe—to myself mostly—what this last year has done to me. I came up with a list. The list represents major paradigm shifts for me. A crisis, a journey, or perhaps the first time that I document (with some thought) feelings that I’ve long had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, the Mormon missionaries have been coming by recently and their visit has caused me to think more about a “faith crisis” I find myself in since about a year ago. These are some of the things that I know I believe for certain. I also list a couple of things that I don’t believe. This feels like a fitting topic for a first blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I DO NOT believe that it is OK for non-LDS Christians to write lists of items that disqualify Mormons from being Christians.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I DO NOT believe that it is OK for LDS to claim that non-LDS Christians do not have the “Fullness of the Gospel” on account of not accepting the Book of Mormon, Joseph Smith, Polygamy et. al.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that the Church (LDS and non) creates an unhealthy and even dangerous attitude towards intimacy and sex.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that all scripture (LDS and non) is fallible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that all scripture is good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that a genuine relationship with oneself is more important than an artificial relationship with “God.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that the universe has seen my story unfold one million times before. I too will grow old and die and be forgotten. I am not unique. I am peacefully comfortable with this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that the best thing that I can do with my time in this beautiful planet, is be the best human being that I can be. Especially to the people who are closest to me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that I have always misunderstood the concept of “God”, and that is OK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that “being true to oneself” is selfish.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that we should be true to our word no matter the cost. This lesson has come at a steep price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe in the power of music to heal, more than in the “power of prayer.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that religion has become an obstacle to #8.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that some people are evil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that most people are kind.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe the following more now than at any other time in my life:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real violence, the violence that I realized was unforgivable, is the violence that we do to ourselves when we’re too afraid to be who we really are.” - Nomi (Sense8, Season 1, Episode 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
