<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Marty Romero</title>
 <link href="http://martyromero.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://martyromero.me/"/>
 <updated>2016-04-10T05:08:13-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://martyromero.me</id>
 <author>
   <name>Marty Romero</name>
   <email>martyromero@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Discovering My Masturbation Myths</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/discovering-my-masturbation-myths"/>
   <updated>2016-04-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/discovering-my-masturbation-myths</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;style&gt;.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed//zRkPU1fKchI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;something-to-hide&quot;&gt;Something to Hide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the summer when I discovered masturbation. It was a wonderful three months that came to an end in September at the start of a new school year. I recall vividly the anxiety I felt over not being able to enjoy quiet mornings romancing myself while mom and my sister were at work. I must have been eleven or twelve and at that age I hadn’t even heard the term “masturbation” and if I had, I wouldn’t have been able to associate it with this beautifully raw gesture that left me numb with joy when I was finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in a household that was NOT sex-friendly. By that I mean that sex was never talked about. We ignored the sexy scenes in R rated movies and pretended that we didn’t understand the inuendos of TV commercials. I was never taught that sex or masturbation was a bad thing, but I picked it up. I learned—like we all do—to NOT talk about it and to hide my natural curiosity about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-story&quot;&gt;My Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t help that I was brough up a Mormon by a wonderful Mexican single mother. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mormonthink.com/QUOTES/masturbation.htm&quot; title=&quot;LDS Quotes on the Topic of Masturbation&quot;&gt;Mormonism teaches implicity and explicity that masturbation is not only wrong, but also sinful&lt;/a&gt;. I grew up listening to the leaders of the Mormon Church say things like :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…If you are tempted to masturbate, think of having to bathe in a tub of worms, and eat several of them as you do the act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a year after I discovered that I could …. the bishop of my local Mormon congregation took it upon himself to gather all the young men twelve to fifteen years old, and graphically describe what masturbation was and how it made young boys “evil”. He described something very different from my experiences. Yet here was the chosen man of God telling me that what I was doing was a “sexual sin” and that sexual sins ranked right next to murder in the eyes of God. To me, my penis and the pleasure that I derived during my quiet mornings at home were special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sad thing about this experience was how it changed me. I was listening to a the words of a man whom I had been taught was Jesus Christs’ mouthpiece tell me that I was “evil” and that I was commiting a sin second in greviousness only to murder. Some of my very first lies &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; have been to myself. I don’t actually remember convincing myself that what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; was doing was &lt;em&gt;NOT&lt;/em&gt; so “evil” and “sinful”. But I must have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I wish someone would have assured me that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The LDS Church leaders were wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That like anything, masturbation could become an unhealthy behavior, but that it is neither a sin nor evil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That being highly sexual and sensitive was not something that I needed to hide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am forty-two years old now and I am married to a wonderful woman. We don’t have a perfect marriage and much of what is wrong has been my own doing. I am just now beginning to understand how damaging it was for me to not have a space where I could be open about sex. And by that I don’t mean that I wish I would have been more promiscuous or sexual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I wish, is that my mother and Church leaders would have sat in the crowd of this  beautifully raw TED talk.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Things I believe (and a couple that I don&#39;t)</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/things-i-believe"/>
   <updated>2015-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/things-i-believe</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have spent a lot of my time trying to describe—to myself mostly—what this last year has done to me. I came up with a list. The list represents major paradigm shifts for me. A crisis, a journey, or perhaps the first time that I document (with some thought) feelings that I’ve long had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, the Mormon missionaries have been coming by recently and their visit has caused me to think more about a “faith crisis” I find myself in since about a year ago. These are some thing that I decided I believe. I also list a couple of things that I don’t believe. This feels like a fitting topic for a first blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I DO NOT believe that it is OK for non-LDS Christians to write lists of items that disqualify Mormons from being Christians.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I DO NOT believe that it is OK for LDS to claim that non-LDS Christians do not have the “Fullness of the Gospel” on account of not accepting the Book of Mormon, Joseph Smith, Polygamy et. al.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that the Church (LDS and non) creates an unhealthy and even dangerous attitude towards intimacy and sex.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that all scripture (LDS and non) is fallible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that all scripture is good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that a genuine relationship with oneself is more important than an artificial relationship with “God.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that the universe has seen my story unfold one million times before. I too will grow old and die and be forgotten. I am not unique. I am peacefully comfortable with this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that the best thing that I can do with my time in this beautiful planet, is be the best human being that I can be. Especially to the people who are closest to me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that I have always misunderstood the concept of “God”, and that is OK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that “being true to oneself” is selfish.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that we should be true to our word no matter the cost. This lesson has come at a steep price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe in the power of music to heal, more than in the “power of prayer.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that religion has become an obstacle to #8.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that some people are evil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that most people are kind.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe the following more now than at any other time in my life: &amp;gt;The real violence, the violence that I realized was unforgivable, is the violence that we do to ourselves when we’re too afraid to be who we really are.” - Nomi (Sense8, Season 1, Episode 2).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
