<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Marty Romero</title>
 <link href="http://martyromero.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://martyromero.me/"/>
 <updated>2016-04-12T13:02:19-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://martyromero.me</id>
 <author>
   <name>Marty Romero</name>
   <email>martyromero@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Dear Cheating Spouse...</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/dear-cheating-spouse"/>
   <updated>2016-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/dear-cheating-spouse</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your first marriage is over. Would you like to create a second one together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You will be rebuilding a new life after an affair; the question becomes, will you be doing it together as a couple, or on your own?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/P2AUat93a8Q&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;- Esther Perel - &lt;em&gt;Why Happy Couples Cheat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Debate Over Graffiti as Crime or Art is Pointless (part 1 of 2)</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/the-debate-over-graffiti-as-crime-or-art-is-pointless"/>
   <updated>2016-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/the-debate-over-graffiti-as-crime-or-art-is-pointless</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/posts/graffiti-good.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;KaterOne, Visions Crew 2005, East Los Angeles.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;KaterOne, Visions Crew 2005, East Los Angeles.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-debate&quot;&gt;The debate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, I wrote graffiti for the thrill, anonymity, and recognition from other graffiti writers. As a graffiti writer, I didn’t realize the passionate debate over graffiti as art or crime like I do now—a discussion that is pointless in my opinion. A more productive question to answer by those on either side of the fence is, what is the role of graffiti in our public space? The obvious answer—some would argue—is that graffiti should NOT play a role and that it ought to be eradicated. Well, I’d like to challenge that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My school newspaper recently wrote an article about how much it was going to cost to remove graffiti from the L.A. river walls. The writer wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…there are no positive effects of graffiti to any community, and those caught doing it should be locked away and the key thrown away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argued that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…because graffiti by definition is a crime, it cannot be approached as anything else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writer did note that commissioned works—even those painted by graffiti artist and clearly graffiti—were NOT “really” graffiti, because they had authorization. The problem with arguments about the legality of graffiti or those that defend it as art is that they ignore aspects of graffiti that relate to how we use our public spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-the-debate-is-pointless&quot;&gt;Why is the debate is pointless&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say that there are no positive contributions by graffiti implies a set of criteria by which we determine what provides and what does not provide value. What is that criterion? Who defines it? Is the criterion accurate? Most people would say that the law sets the criteria, but it would only take a basic history lesson to point out that some laws can be unjust. When we submit law a the ultimate criteria for what is and what is not legal or of value, then we must submit the amount of corporate control, immigration, civil rights, etc. through that criterion—which we don’t. If we solely rely on the denotation of graffiti to ascribe its value, we are forced to accept that what is natural is often socially constructed to the interest of some more than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-graffitis-contribution&quot;&gt;What is graffiti’s contribution?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I propose that graffiti and graffiti writers’ contributions are valuable, particularly when we speak of public space. The value is in recognizing the socially constructed truths and political agendas that influence our culture, society and communities in ways that we may not want. Graffiti keeps these truths and agendas on check by constantly challenging them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, people might argue that advertising or popular culture does not influence them, but what they mean is that the apparent messages of these cultural productions do not influence them. Adds that try to sell Wendy’s instead of McDonalds, or Pepsi instead of Coke may not have a real impact on individuals. But the underlying myth of consumerism that these ads present when added up to all of the thousands of unrecognized retellings of the consumer myth do influence the nation into believing that the myth of consumerism is not a myth, but is the natural state of human affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today, communities produce almost nothing. As an employee or a student, we are required to produce some things: reports, call logs, sales, etc. But outside of our role as employees, or students, what do we produce? Most of us do not grow or raise our food, we don’t make our clothes, and only a few in the community make their own music or entertainment. Some participate in athletics once in a while, but other than sports and dancing there is little left in society for humans to produce. Instead, we have become consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each time that graffiti is produced, it speaks against the consumerism myth such that it becomes an identity marker of a community.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Discovering My Masturbation Myths</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/discovering-my-masturbation-myths"/>
   <updated>2016-04-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/discovering-my-masturbation-myths</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;style&gt;.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed//zRkPU1fKchI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;something-to-hide&quot;&gt;Something to Hide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the summer when I discovered masturbation. It was an incredible three months that came to an end in September at the start of a new school year. I recall the anxiety vividly that I felt over not being able to enjoy quiet mornings romancing myself while mom and my sister were at work. I must have been eleven or twelve that summer. At that age, I hadn’t heard the term “masturbation”, and if I had, I wouldn’t have been able to associate it with the beautifully raw gesture that left me numb with joy when I was finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in a household that was NOT sex-friendly. By that, I mean that sex was a topic not to be spoken of openly. We ignored the “sexy” scenes in R rated movies and pretended that we didn’t understand the innuendos of TV commercials. No one ever told me that sex or masturbation was wrong, but it’s a lesson that I learned regardless. I learned—like we all do—to NOT talk about sex and to hide my natural curiosity about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-story&quot;&gt;My Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t help that I was raised up in the Mormon Church. My mother is a beautiful traditional Mexican mom. Single that she was, she raised my sister and I as best she knew how. What that meant in practical terms is that others imparted a lot of our ethical, moral, and just general-life lessons. Many of those lessons came from the Mormon Church.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mormonthink.com/QUOTES/masturbation.htm&quot; title=&quot;LDS Quotes on the Topic of Masturbation&quot;&gt;Mormonism teaches implicitly and explicitly that masturbation is not only wrong but sinful&lt;/a&gt;. I grew up listening to leaders of the Mormon Church say things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…If you are tempted to masturbate, think of having to bathe in a tub of worms, and eat several of them as you do the act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a year after I discovered that I could… well, you know. The bishop of my local Mormon Church congregation took it upon himself to gather all the young men twelve to fifteen years old, and graphically describe what masturbation was and how it made young boys “evil.” He described something very different from my experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “man of God” was telling me that what I was doing was a “sexual sin” and that “sexual sins” ranked right next to murder in the eyes of God. To me, the pleasure that I derived during my quiet mornings at home were special. The sad thing about this experience is that it encapsulated the attitude towards sex and masturbation by everyone who was raising me, and it changed me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had learned that my bishop was Jesus Christs’ mouthpiece. And he was telling me that I was “evil.” So, some of my very first lies &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; have been to myself. I don’t remember convincing myself that I was &lt;em&gt;NOT&lt;/em&gt;, but I must have!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I wish someone would have assured me that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The LDS Church leaders were wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That like anything, masturbation could become an unhealthy behavior, but that it is neither evil nor sinful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That being highly sexual and sensitive was not something that I needed to hide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am forty-two years old now, and I am married to a beautiful woman. We don’t have a perfect marriage—much of what is wrong with our companionship has been my own doing. It seems clear in retrospect that a lot of the challenges today go back to those early lessons. I am just now beginning to understand how damaging it was for me not to have a space where I could be open about sex. And by that, I don’t mean that I wish I could have been more promiscuous or sexual, just more open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I wish, is that my mother and my Church leaders could have been made to sit through this beautiful and raw TED talk. Thank you &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.teeshamorgan.com/&quot; title=&quot;Dr. Teesha Morgan&quot;&gt;Dr. Teesha Morgan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Last Night I Saw My Dad</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/the-last-night-i-saw-my-dad"/>
   <updated>2016-03-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/the-last-night-i-saw-my-dad</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/posts/dad-last-night.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My dad standing in front of a palm tree.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em class=&quot;image-caption clearfix&quot;&gt;In his 30s, dad while serving time at Islas Marias Federal Prison in Mexico.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mom&quot;&gt;Mom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mom left dad when I was five years old. During the weeks leading up to her decision, she thought of every possible excuse to stay, but there was a way out of every single one. Now and then mom opens up about the things that she considered. She feared not being able to raise two kids on her own. My sister was born without her left leg and caring for her would be difficult. She also thought about how much my sister and I would miss dad, me in particular—I was his favorite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once decided, mom had to figure out a way to leave without raising the suspicion that we would not be coming back. She packed all of our clothes in boxes and had them shipped to my aunt in &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/THHOTWBs8ZQ&quot; title=&quot;The colonia where I grew up&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ensenada&lt;/a&gt; a few days before we left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step in her plan was to pack wood and a few rocks in empty boxes and stack them neatly inside the closet. The purpose was to give my dad the impression that we were coming back and that she was merely making sure our “clothes” would be neatly waiting for us upon our return. Mom had had enough. Dad cheated on her, abused her (verbally, physically, and sexually). Mom was ready to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dad&quot;&gt;Dad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dad drove us to the bus station. While we waited to board the bus, dad kept me close to him. I remember holding his hand and feeling that he didn’t want to let go of me. I thought he had figured it out! That somehow he knew we weren’t coming back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we boarded the bus, he knelt beside me and kissed me on my cheek. I remember the prickly feeling of his mustache against my face and the strong smell of cigar. He tightened his grip on my hand and whispered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am going to follow the bus for as long as I can, so be on the look out for me ok?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;me&quot;&gt;Me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those were the last words he said to me. That was his way of saying good-bye. On the bus, mom didn’t say much, but she held my hand the entire trip. As the bus got on the road, I kept looking out the window for dad’s blue El Camino with the dirty white camper. A minute later, I saw his car cut in front of us. That gesture was as if he were talking to me and I burned it into memory. I stared at his car through the window, afraid to look away for fear that I might lose him. Some short distance later, I saw dad’s car make a right turn, but the bus that we were on kept on going straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the years went by and I got older, I always yearned to tell him that I had seen his car that night many years ago. And that I loved him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dad passed away ten years ago today. Sometimes I still miss him.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Things I believe (and two that I don&#39;t)</title>
   <link href="http://martyromero.me/things-i-believe"/>
   <updated>2015-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://martyromero.me/things-i-believe</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have spent a lot of my time trying to describe—to myself mostly—what this last year has done to me. I came up with a list. The list represents major paradigm shifts for me. A crisis, a journey, or perhaps the first time that I document (with some thought) feelings that I’ve long had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, the Mormon missionaries have been coming by recently and their visit has caused me to think more about a “faith crisis” I find myself in since about a year ago. These are some of the things that I know I believe for certain. I also list a couple of things that I don’t believe. This feels like a fitting topic for a first blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I DO NOT believe that it is OK for non-LDS Christians to write lists of items that disqualify Mormons from being Christians.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I DO NOT believe that it is OK for LDS to claim that non-LDS Christians do not have the “Fullness of the Gospel” on account of not accepting the Book of Mormon, Joseph Smith, Polygamy et. al.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that the Church (LDS and non) creates an unhealthy and even dangerous attitude towards intimacy and sex.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that all scripture (LDS and non) is fallible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that all scripture is good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that a genuine relationship with oneself is more important than an artificial relationship with “God.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that the universe has seen my story unfold one million times before. I too will grow old and die and be forgotten. I am not unique. I am peacefully comfortable with this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that the best thing that I can do with my time in this beautiful planet, is be the best human being that I can be. Especially to the people who are closest to me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that I have always misunderstood the concept of “God”, and that is OK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that “being true to oneself” is selfish.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that we should be true to our word no matter the cost. This lesson has come at a steep price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe in the power of music to heal, more than in the “power of prayer.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that religion has become an obstacle to #8.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that some people are evil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that most people are kind.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe the following more now than at any other time in my life:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The real violence, the violence that I realized was unforgivable, is the violence that we do to ourselves when we’re too afraid to be who we really are.” - Nomi (Sense8, Season 1, Episode 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
